<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Common Lisp on jean0t blog</title>
    <link>https://jean0t.github.io/tags/common-lisp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Common Lisp on jean0t blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 22:02:24 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jean0t.github.io/tags/common-lisp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Simping for Common Lisp</title>
      <link>https://jean0t.github.io/posts/simping-for-common-lisp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 22:02:24 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jean0t.github.io/posts/simping-for-common-lisp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;macros&#34;&gt;MACROS&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That is the answer, simple and direct. Macros are the greatest tool regarding common lisp, it gives us more flexibility but also privacy.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;What do I mean by both terms &amp;lsquo;privacy&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;flexibility&amp;rsquo;?&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Privacy because it can hide functions in the package, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to expose your functions to make it work, just as you export a class with private methods, with macros you can expose simply an interface that will call those functions internally and be nice syntatically.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Regarding flexibility it is also pretty direct, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to call functions everytime, you can make an structure that organizes the code itself with functions and other structures internally so you have a more coherent design and a DSL if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Common Lisp Is My Favorite</title>
      <link>https://jean0t.github.io/posts/why-common-lisp-is-my-favorite/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2025 00:37:00 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jean0t.github.io/posts/why-common-lisp-is-my-favorite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came from a background of python/golang programming, my first contact with programming was with python, then I studied C to get to know systems programming and understand better about memory with pointers&amp;hellip; golang was kind of my favorite language during a lot of time, because it has a simple and direct syntax with some built in niceties like map or slices (which in C must be done manually).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However after some time I got kinda bored, the tools were amazing but I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel the ecstasy of exploring new features or syntax, I had heard about lisp before, although I disregarded it because I thought it was esoteric (which was synonym of uselessly complex and hard) to do things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
